All right, now we're doing the final part of the Capstone Project walkthrough.
はい Capstone プロジェクトの説明の最後の部分です
Yes. So, previously we've covered getting waypoints,
はいこれまで ウェイポイントおよび公開された最終ウェイポイントの取得
published the final waypoints,
DBWノードによる車両制御
controlling the car with the DBW node and the logic behind the traffic light detection.
そして 交通信号検出の裏にあるロジックについて述べてきました
Okay. Now we actually have to take those states of
いいですか実際に
the traffic light and put them to use on the waypoints.
信号機の状態を検出し ウェイポイントで使うようにしなければなりません
Yes. So let's have a look.
はいでは実際に見てみましょう
We're revisiting one of the files that we were
先程まで作業していたファイルの一つ
just working with, the waypoint_updater.py.
"waypoint_updater.py"を再び見ていきましょう
So, if we check that out,
それで確認すると
we did a lot of this work already.
多くのことを行ったことがわかります
So, it looks like all of these updates are happening and publish waypoints.
これらすべての更新が行われており ウェイポイントを公開しているように見えます
So now we have this "generate_lane" function.
今 "generate_lane"関数があります
Basically, the idea is that we're going to take
基本的には ウェイポイントを
the waypoints and update their velocity is based on how we want the car to behave.
取得し それらの速度を更新するという考え方は 車両の挙動に基づいています
So, if we have some traffic light information coming in,
信号機情報が入ってきたら
we want to slow the car down leading up to the stop line in front of the traffic light.
車の速度を落として 信号の前にある停止線まで進みたいと思います
That's just as easy as telling
ウェイポイントの特性速度の値が
that waypoints' property velocity value that twists linear.
線形であることを伝えるのと同じくらい簡単です
This is the velocity that you should be going at and then there's
これは進むべき速度であり、車が自動で
some extra logic in auto where that helps us take the car to that speed.
その速度にするのを助ける追加ロジックです
Well, all we have to do is we update the twist.linear.x, I think it is.
あとは twist.linear.x を更新するだけでいいのです
Seems pretty straightforward.
とても簡単に思えます
So, we do have a new subscriber in this and that's the traffic.
新しい加入者がおり これがトラフィックです
That's kind of important now.
これを行うことは重要です
If we didn't have already,
この作業を行っていない場合
there it is and its callback should be pretty straightforward,
コールバックはかなり簡単なはずであり
that stop lying waypoint index.
ウェイポイント インデックスを横切ることはありません
Great. So what is happening with this generate lane?
書けましたか?では、この"generate_lane"で何が起きているのでしょうか？
So it looks like we're using this final lane
最後の車線を使っているように見えますが
and that's actually what is the output of this generate lane.
実際には この生成車線の出力となっています
Yeah. And once we have final lane,
はい最終車線が完成したら
we can just publish on the final lane directly.
最終車線に直接公開するだけです
Okay. We're working with our waypoints from before right?
これで 前からウェイポイントを使って取り組んでいますか?
So it looks like we're doing the same process
基本となるウェイポイントを探し 接合する
of looking at our base waypoints and splicing it.
のと 同じプロセスを行っているように見えます
Yeah. So we create a lane and a message,
はい車線とメッセージを作成し
and we get the closest index from our cars.
自分の車両から一番近いインデックスを得ます
So it's very similar to what we've done before,
私たちが以前にやったことと非常によく似ています
we get the farthest index which is
最も遠いインデックスは
the closest index plus the number of lookahead waypoints.
最も近いインデックスにルックアヘッド ウェイポイントの数を加えたものです
Okay. Just like last time?
これで 前と同じように思えます
Yeah. And then base waypoints,
はいそして ウェイポイントを基準にして
we're going to slice the base
最も近いインデックスから最も遠いインデックスに基準となる
lane.waypoints from our closest index to the farthest index.
lane.waypoints を結合します
So that's going to be a list of waypoints.
それで ウェイポイントのリストになります
If that stop lying waypoint is not negative one,
もし、その"stopline_wp"がマイナスでない場合、
or if it's just farther than we care about,
注意すべきことがある場合は
we're actually going to do some work here.
ここで作業を行います
So if it is negative one or if it's further than we care about,
もし、その"stopline_wp"がマイナスでない場合、 注意すべきことがある場合は
then we just publish the base waypoints directly.
"base_waypoints"直接公開するだけです
Yeah, leave it alone.
はい そのままにしましょう
Yeah, because we didn't detect any traffic light data that we're concerned about.
心配している信号機のデータは検出されませんでした
Yeah. No need to make any modifications.
はい変更する必要はありません
Else, we have this decelerate waypoints,
そうでなければ 減速したウェイポイントを持っています
and that's what we're getting at the base waypoints in that closest index.
これは 最も近いインデックスの基本的なウェイポイントで得ているものです
And so, we want to be a little careful here.
ここで 注意が必要です
The decelerate waypoints were basically just going to be
減速ウェイポイントについては 基本的には
creating some new waypoints message types.
いくつかの新しいウェイポイント メッセージのタイプを作成することになります
Couldn't just modify on top of it?
変更するだけではできませんか?
We probably don't want to modify our base waypoints.
基本的なウェイポイントを変更したくないでしょう
So, as we discussed previously,
以前説明したように
that message comes in only once and we want to keep the base waypoints preserved.
メッセージは一度だけ送信されるので 基本的なウェイポイントを保存しておきたいと思います
That would get pretty messy, wouldn't it?
複雑になりませんか?
Yeah. If we started changing the properties where base waypoints,
はいウェイポイントの基準となる場所でプロパティの変更を開始した場合
then we sort of lose them if you drive back over the same waypoints-
同じウェイポイントを越えて運転した場合 ウェイポイントを失います
May make your ride very uncomfortable.
その場合 乗り心地は悪くなります
Yeah. Cars may do some strange things.
はい自動車は奇妙な動きをするかもしれません
So we want to basically create a new list of
基本的に
waypoints but use some of the information from those base waypoints.
ウェイポイントの新しいリストを作成したい場合は 基本ウェイポイントからの情報の一部を使用したいと思います
Now that you know how to not sabotage the project,
プロジェクトを妨害しない方法がわかりました
what's the proper way of doing it?
どんな適切な方法がありますか?
So, the proper way is that we're going to enumerate
正しい方法は 分割したウェイポイントのリストの上に
over the sliced list of waypoints there,
エミュレートすることです
and we're going to create a new waypoint message and we're going to
新しいウェイポイントメッセージを作成し
set the pose to the base waypoint pose.
ポーズをベースウェイ ポイント ポーズに設定します
The position of the waypoint isn't going to change any.
ウェイポイントの位置は変わりません
And that pose also contains
ポーズには
the orientation and so the orientation of waypoints should stay the same.
方位も含まれているため ウェイポイントの方位も同じであるべきです
And then, we want to figure out what the stop index should be.
ストップ インデックスがどうあるべきかを把握したいと思います
And because we've taken a slice,
スライスしたため
there's a little bit of math here to figure out what the-
理解するために少し数学を学ぶ必要があります
So we want to go back a little bit, right?
少し戻りましょうね
So we have that stop line,
停止線があるため
and then we have that closest index and also have this minus two,
最も近いインデックスから 2 を引きます
that's because this is the exact center of the car.
これは車両の正確な中心であるためです
So then it would just be a little bit over the line itself.
車両は停止線をすぐ超えたところにあります
Yeah. So if we don't have a minus two in there,
はいここで 2 を引かないと
we will stop with the centre of the car right on the line.
車両の中心部が停止線に来てしまいます
Okay. That's dangerous.
OK危険です
Yeah. So you put
はいそこで
the minus two or maybe minus three waypoints in there
ウェイポイントから 2 または 3 を引き
to make the nose of the car stop behind the line.
車両のノーズが停止線の後ろに来るようにします
And so this list of waypoints, remember,
ウェイポイントのリストは覚えておいてください
starts at the closest index.
最も近いインデックスで開始します
We sliced from the closest index to
最も近いインデックスから
the closest index plus however many look away head waypoints.
最も近いインデックスにスライスしますが 多くの人はウェイポイントに注意しません
It's kind of like a waypoint distance of how
停止する必要がある信号から
far away from this light that we need to stop at.
どれほど離れた距離のウェイポイントなのかなどです
So, we can just calculate the distance using our distance function right here.
ここにある"distance"関数を使って距離を計算することができます
Yeah, the distance function we pass in that list of waypoints
ウェイポイントのリストで渡す距離関数
or whatever index we are in this enumeration and then the index of the stop.
または 一覧にあるインデックスは 停止のインデックスとなります
Iterate through and add them up, add up the distances.
繰り返して 数値を合計し 距離を合計します
Yeah. So, the distance function does a linear piecewise distance.
はいdistance 関数は線形の区分的距離をとります
So it just sums up the distance from one waypoint to the next.
あるウェイポイントから次のウェイポイントまでの距離を合計するだけです
All the line segments?
すべての車線の区分ですか?
No, only the line segments between waypoints.
いいえ ウェイポイント間の車線の区分のみです
And then finally, we can figure out what the velocity is.
最後に 速度が何であるかを理解することができます
Sure. And distance will return zero if "i" is bigger than the stop index. It's good.
はい"i"が停止インデックスよりも大きい場合 distance はゼロを返しますいいでしょう
It wouldn't really make sense unless it was looping all the way back around.
前に戻ってループしていない限り 実際には意味がありません
Right.
分かりますね
There'd be some logic check right away saying "Oh wait,
ロジック チェックが行われます 「ちょっと待ってください
I'm supposed to go until the difference between these is zero and it's already."
差がゼロになるまで進めることになっていますが 既にゼロです 」
Yeah. So let me calculate the velocity.
はい速度を計算しましょう
So, tell me what's going on here.
どうなっているのでしょう
I think it'll help if we actually visually see what's going on here.
何が起こっているのかを実際に視覚的に確認すれば 役に立つと思います
So, if we draw it out,
描くと
what does this curve looks like?
カーブはどのようになるでしょうか?
Yeah, so if we draw this,
これを描く場合
we have the velocity,
速度があり
and it's following this nice square root function here,
平方根関数に従っています
so as the distance between our waypoint and the stop waypoint becomes small,
ウェイポイントと停止ウェイポイントの間の距離が小さくなるように
we're following this profile.
このプロフィールを追跡しています
Yeah. And then we have our speed limit right
はい制限速度が高いため
here and we're being careful not to go over that.
制限速度が超えないように注意します
And then it's falling down and
速度が減少し
you can see though that it is getting sharper as it's decreasing as well.
同様に減少しているので カーブが鋭角になっていることがわかります
Right.
分かりますね
It's like you're just lightly putting on
ブレーキ ペダルを軽く乗せただけで
the brake pedal and then at the very end you're pressing as hard as you can.
最後にできる限り強く踏み込んだようになります
Yeah. Then we have waypoint speed set to zero after that.
はいウェイポイント速度をゼロに設定します
So here we have a square root function.
ここには 平方根関数があります
Now this I used because this is very similar to what's in the waypoint loader code.
ウェイポイント ローダーのコードにあるものと非常によく似ているので これを使用しました
If you've gone through and read the waypoint loader code,
ウェイポイント ローダーのコードを読み終えてから
you'll see that the waypoints are decelerated at the beginning.
ウェイポイントが最初は減速しているのがわかります
It accelerates from zero to the regular waypoint velocity
ゼロから通常の中間地点速度まで加速するため
and then at the end of a waypoint list it's decelerating to zero again.
ウェイポイントリストの最後で再び減速してゼロになります
Right away I can see that it's making sense
理にかなっていることがわかります
because this velocity is dependent on this distance parameter.
速度は距離パラメーターに依存しているからです
So, the larger the distance, the larger the velocity.
距離が大きいほど速度は速くなります
But when this distance gets really small,
距離が本当に小さくなると
it makes sense and my velocity should be really small as
理にかなっている必要があり 速度は遅くなります
well because it's preparing to stop and it's decelerating.
車両は 停止する準備をしているため 減速しているからです
Yeah exactly. So, as we get closer to that stop index,
ええ そのとおりです停止インデックスに近づくにつれて
the distance becomes very small and the velocity gets to zero.
距離は非常に小さくなり 速度はゼロになります
Yeah. And this square root is just going to actually help shape that, right?
はいこの平方根は実際にそれを形作るのを援助するだけですよね?
Yeah. Now, you may not want to use a square root.
はい平方根を使用しなくても構いません
If you look at the profile of this deceleration,
この減速のプロファイルを見ると
you'll see that the square root becomes sort of steep as you get close to the stop line.
停止線に近づくにつれて 平方根が急勾配になることがわかります
You're taking the derivative of it that rate is getting pretty sharp,
平方根の終わり近くで 速度がかなり急になっており
pretty high near the end of that square root.
高くなっている部分を微分します
Yeah. So instead of a square root, you could just
はい平方根の代わりに
multiply by a constant. So you get some linear.
定数を掛けることができますいくつかの線形を得ることができます
Could try to make it linear?
線形化することができますか?
Yeah. Some linear deceleration.
はいいくつかの線形があります
Nice. Yes.
これで OK ですはい
Yeah, if you want to fit a nice s curve,
はい 適切な s 曲線を適用し
have a nice smooth deceleration,
なめらかな減速をしたい場合
then that can also work.
機能します
Continuous derivative maybe.
連続微分かもしれません
So, if velocity is less than one,
もし速度が 1 より小さければ
we just return zero, why is that?
0 に戻りますが なぜでしょうか?
Basically if the velocity is small enough, we just return zero.
基本的に速度が十分小さければ ゼロを返します
And then we're just taking that and we have this min,
時間をとっているだけであるため
so that's the velocity that we just figured out and this twist.linear.x.
速度と twist.linear.x を検出しました
Yeah. So the square root can become very large as the distance is large,
はい距離が大きいと平方根は非常に大きくなるため
and so, we don't want to set
停止ウェイポイントから遠く離れている場合
a really large velocity if we're a long way away from the stop waypoint.
大きな速度を設定したくはありません
We'd rather just keep the velocity that was given for the waypoints before.
ウェイポイントに与えられた速度をそのままにしておきます
So we treat that as the speed limit basically.
基本的に制限速度として扱います
Yeah.
はい
All the velocities on the waypoints are the speed limit and there's no reason we
ウェイポイント上のすべての速度が制限速度であり
ever want to go higher than that unless we're trying some very interesting logic.
非常に興味深い論理を試しているのでなければ これ以上は必要ありません
So we keep the speed limit and then,
制限速度を守り
as the square root becomes smaller
平方根が小さくなるにつれて
then the speed limit we switch over to that square root velocity.
平方根速度に切り替える速度制限になります
And then we just append that onto our list in return that list.
リストに追加して リストを返します
And so, we should have a list of newly created waypoints for our lane.
車線用に新しく作成したウェイポイントのリストを用意する必要があります
And then we just return that lane and we just published that.
その車線を返して 公表したばかりです
Yeah.
はい
That looks like it's it actually.
実物にように見えます
Yeah, that should be it. There are a few things to watch out for here.
これがその場所です注意することがいくつかあります
If you have a very large list,
非常に大きなリストがある場合は
you want to make sure that you slice
更新を始める前に 必ず
the base lane waypoints before you start updating them.
ベースとなる車線のウェイポイントを分割してください
So if you have to iterate over
毎回 ベースとなる車線のウェイポイントのセット全体を反復して
the entire set of baseline waypoints each time and do this update,
この更新を行う必要がある場合
there wouldn't be very efficient.
それほど効率的ではありません
And I think it's particularly important for this
これが特に重要な点です
because then you can introduce a lot of latency in the code,
コードに多くの待ち時間を導入することができますが
and that by the time your updated waypoints actually get to the car,
更新されたウェイポイントに実際に車両が到達するまでに
the car's moved past them.
車両はウェイポイントを通過します
So we want to be efficient with speed here,
スピードを効率的にしたいですが
nothing's happening as fast as possible.
速くしても何が起こらないことがあります
So just make sure to slice beforehand.
事前に分割するようにしてください
And avoid any latency.
待ち時間を避けなければなりません
Awesome. So, now we can actually get the car driving around following waypoints,
素晴らしい実際に車両は以下のウェイポイントを運転できますが
obeying traffic lights and slowing down for those traffic lights and stopping.
信号機の指示に従い 信号機において速度を落として停止します
All right. Now we've completed the entirety of the walkthrough.
OKチュートリアルの全体を完了しました
Yeah.
はい
What have we learned?
何を学びましたか?
So, we've learned to update the waypoints in this list.
このリストのウェイポイントを更新することを学びました
We've basically learned to publish
基本的に
base waypoints to the set of final waypoints in front of the car.
ベースのウェイポイントを車の前にある一連の最終的なウェイポイントに公開することを学びました
Yeah.
はい
What else?
ほかにありますか?
We learned how to control the car,
これらのウェイポイントを追跡するために
to follow these waypoints.
車をコントロールする方法を学びました
That's right. I guess we also learned about traffic light detection,
そうです信号機の検出についても学んだと思います
the logic of detecting
信号機を検出し
the traffic light and sending the correct waypoint from the traffic light.
信号機から正しいウェイポイントを送信するロジックです
Right. And then finally,
分かりますね最終的に
how to actually stop at that light.
信号機で停止する方法を学びました
Yeah.
はい
And slow down your velocity.
車速をゆっくりします
So, other than the traffic light model,
信号モデル以外に
this should be everything that you would need to drive the car, right?
車を運転するために必要なものすべてを学びましたね
Yeah, that's right.
そうですね
Yeah, great.
うん いいですね
That's awesome.
素晴らしいです
Yeah. So, thanks for joining us for this series of walkthroughs.
はい一連のチュートリアルをご利用いただきありがとうございます
Yeah, thank you.
なるほど ありがとう
And good luck.
頑張ってください